Guide to the James Rorty Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Rorty papers
1941-1970
YCAL MSS 835
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.91
(3 boxes)
Manuscripts, printed works, correspondence, and professional papers of the writer James Rorty. The Writings series includes Rorty's typescript and manuscript essays on social issues, civil rights, and political activism, two of his poems, and printed works. The Correspondence series includes three typed letters between Rorty's wife Winifred Rorty and Matthew Josephson; letters between Rorty and Jerré E. Tanner regarding Tanner's setting of Rorty's poem "A Spring Garland" for voice and piano, with autograph manuscript score; and one typed letter from Rorty to Ruth Aley and one typed letter from Rorty to Tom Sloane. The Professional Papers include Rorty's curriculum vitae.
Rorty, James, 1890-1973
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Rorty.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
James Rorty (1890-1973)
James Rorty (1890-1973), writer, journalist, poet, and father of philosopher Richard Rorty.
Scope and Contents
Manuscripts, printed works, correspondence, and professional papers of the writer James Rorty. The Writings series includes Rorty's typescript and manuscript essays on social issues, civil rights, and political activism, two of his poems, and printed works. The Correspondence series includes three typed letters between Rorty's wife Winifred Rorty and Matthew Josephson; letters between Rorty and Jerré E. Tanner regarding Tanner's setting of Rorty's poem "A Spring Garland" to music, as well as the original sheet music; and one typed letter from Rorty to Ruth Aley and one typed letter from Rorty to Tom Sloane. The Professional Papers include Rorty's curriculum vitae.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Writings, 1941-1965. II. Correspondence, 1965-1969. III. Professional Papers, 1970, undated.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Political activists -- United States; Journalists -- United States; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Civil Rights movements -- United States; Social movements -- United States; American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; United States -- Social conditions -- 1960-1980; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Journalists -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Political activists -- United States -- 20th Century; Rorty, James, 1890-1973; Josephson, Matthew, 1899-1978; Tanner, Jerré E.; Aley, Ruth
- Writings, 1941-1965; Series I; 0.42; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Manuscripts and Printed Material.
  - Manuscripts
    - It Happened Here, manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Final Conquest, typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The End of the Line, typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - We Open the Gates: Labor's Fight for Equality, typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - At the Court of Love, typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - A Suburb in Purgatory, typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Gift of Henry Vann, typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Wound and the Arrow, typescripts, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - The Communications Crisis, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - The Metaphysics of Birth Control, typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - The Criminal Society, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Roadway to the Future, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Time and Western Man, typescripts, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - The Reluctant Philosopher-King, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - TVA and the Common Mooring, typescript fragments, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - California in the Twenties, typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Viking's Apprentice, typescripts, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Reluctant Patriarch, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - The Epoch of Man's Becoming, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - The South Jamaica Story, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - A Novel about Anti-Gentilism, typescript book review, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified essay on advertising, typescript fragment, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Prayer, typescript poem, signed, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - The Revolution Absolute, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Scope and Contents
      Typescript poem, with typescript essay on ecology
  - Printed Material
    - América Indígena, 1960 July (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Contains Rorty's article ¿Hay Descriminación en México?
    - Brother Jim Crow by Rorty, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Commentary, 1954, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Two issues containing Rorty's Desegregation Along the Mason-Dixon Line.
    - Common Sense, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Contains Rorty's Food for Freedom
    - The Commonweal, 1944-1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Three issues, containing the Rorty writings A Study in Cultural Elephantiasis (12 May 1944); Did They Know It Was Loaded (3 June 1949); and Independence, Like It or Not (8 September 1961).
    - How St. Louis Broke the Race Barrier by Rorty, 1957 April 20 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - March of the Machine by Rorty, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - The New Leader, 1948-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Three issues, containing the Rorty writings VOGT: Soil and the Future, reviewed by Rorty (11 September 1948); John T. Flynn on the China Story (14 January 1952); a letter to the editor (28 January 1952); and Is McCarthy Subversive (16 August 1954)
    - Toward the Integration of Our Schools: Final Report of the Commission on Integration, circa 1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Unfitting the Unborn by Rorty and N. Philip Norman, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - We Open the Gates: Labor's Fight for Equality by Rorty and Harry Fleischman, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1965-1969; Series II; 2
  Series II is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Aley, Ruth, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Josephson, Matthew, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sloane, Tom, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Tanner, Jerré, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes letters between Tanner and Rorty regarding the creation of sheet music by Tanner based on Rorty's poem cycle A Spring Garland, as well as the original sheet music.
- Professional Papers, 1970, undated; Series III (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Series III is arranged chronologically.